Preliminary Inventory of the American Educational Research Association Records
Hoover Institution Archives
- Strategic Planning Task Force (SPTF), 1997 April
- AERA (Box 95)
  - General
  - Annual meetings - Scheduling
- Curricula vitae and biographies, 1998
- Division L - Educational Policy and Politics
- Invitational conference, - Participant list, 1996 May 31
- Lectureship
- Research policy notes
- Vancouver convention - Correspondence
- Washington, D.C.
- Wilson, William Julius
  - Articles
  - Biography and profile
  - Correspondence
- AERA (Box 96)
  - Citations
  - Committee appointments, 1996 May
  - Committees
  - Nominations Committee
  - Stationery
  - Strategic Planning Committee
- Citizenship session - "Citizenship Education in Multicultural Societies"
- Correspondence
  - Cole, Michael
  - Delpit, Lisa D.
  - Gardner, Howard
    (Harvard University)
  - Gillborn, David
    (Institute of Education, University of London)
  - Harding, Sandra
  - Heath, Shirley Brice
  - Hill Collins, Patricia
  - Hope King, Sabrina
  - Jackson, Anthony
  - Lieberman, Ann
  - Lightfoot, Sara Lawrence
  - Moll, Luis C.
  - Peterson, Penelope L.
  - Schoenfeld, Alan
  - Sleeter, Christine
  - Takaki, Ronald
  - White, Richard
  - Wong Fillmore, Lily
- Cortès, Carlos E. - Profile
- Educational Researcher - Columns
- Letters received
- Photograph
- National Institutes of Health, Childrens health materials, 1997-1998 (Box 100)
- Reading Initiative research, 1997-1998
  - General (3 folders)
  - Meeting, July 30-31, 1997 (Box 101)
  - Volunteer tutoring programs (reading research), 1997 (Box 101)
  - "Reading by Nine", 1997 (Box 101-102)
  - Members of the committee, 1997 (Box 101)
  - Meeting and final report, July 1997
  - General, 1997-1998
  - Ad hoc literacy committee meeting notes, April 3, 1997 (Box 101-102)
  - Correspondence, September 30, 1997
  - Correspondence on the hearing on national exams, July 17-18 1997
  - Notes from teleconference for ad hoc committee on reading, May 12, 1997
  - Ad hoc reading committee on assignments, March; May 13, 1997
  - Article on the brain, April 4, 1997
  - "The American Reads Challenge" work study packet, February 1997
  - "The American Reads Challenge", May 1997
  - "American Reads Challenge" legislation and background, April 28, 1997
  - National exam, April 14, 1997
  - Reading tutors - Barbara Wasik, August 1997
  - Resumes, May 1997
  - Whole school reform, September 1997
- Reading, National Institute on Child Health and Human Development (NICHD), 1997 (Box 102)
- Reading Initiative research
  - Reading briefing draft, undated
  - Correspondence and meeting, March 1997
  - Ad hoc reading committee on assignments, March; May, 1997
  - "Reading by Nine", 1997
  - "Reading Excellence Act", March 1998
- American Educational Research Association testing symposium, June 5, 1991
- Ann Lieberman testing project, 1992
- Materials associated with indirect costs, 1996 (Box 103)
- Materials associated with "Flexibility and Coordination" legislation, 1996
- "Symposium on Effective Schools", 1990
  Scope and Content note
  In 1990 a congressional staff member, working for the Democratic majority, undertook to design a symposium on effective schools to demonstrate the important contribution of federal funding in stimulating school improvement. A planning committee of education groups was formed, including AERA, papers were written by scholars and practitioners, a conference was held, and a Committee Report was issued.
- Government relations materials
  - Education First Alliance, 1994-1996
    Beginning after the congressional elections in 1994, the Republicans began a concerted effort to eliminate the U.S. Department of Education, which had been established by President Carter. AERA joined forces with a coalition of education organizations to save the department. A comprehensive response was developed which included telemarketing strategies as well as more conventional advocacy tactics. Ultimately, the Republican leadership dropped its plan for a frontal assault on the agency.
  - Testimony by staff and association representatives, 1988
  - Creation of the "National Board for Professional Teaching Standards", 1988-1990 (Box 104)
    In the early days of the National Board, AERA was called on for advice about the need for additional research to provide a foundation for the proposed activities, as well as for guidance and support with regard to securing federal funding for this purpose. AERA ultimately supported a sole-source contract and federal funding to the National Board for conducting necessary research and instrument development
  - "Research Contributions to Educational Improvement" report, 1983
    In 1983 AERA submitted an "unsolicited grant application" to the Department of Education. The proposal called for bringing together researchers and practitioners to investigate the topic of research contributions to educational improvement.
    Files contain individual chapters prepared by selected scholards, a final report to the Department, and a summary authored by George Kaplan (Items for an Agenda: Educational Research and the Reports on Excellence) based on the chapters
- James A. Banks, council meeting, March 24, 1997 (Box 105)
- Committees, 1997
- Planning task force, 1996
- Minorities committee, 1996-1997
- "AERA Act", 1970
- Reading task force, Peterson, March 1997
- Brochures, 1993, 1996, 1997
- Tuttle report, 1996
- Strategic planning, November 1996
- Council, 1996-1998 (Box 106)
- Schedule, 1998
- President's Pin, 1998
- Hakuta panels and conferences, 1998-1999
- Awards session, March 3, 1998
- Presidential reception, February 1998
- Party, April 1998
- Baker, February 1998
- "Diversity and Citizenship in Multicultural Societies", January 1998
- Payment forms, No Date
- William Russell, undated
- Presidential citations, 1998
- Professor Watkins letter, February 10, 1998
- List Servs, March 1998
- William Russell resignation letter, February 26, 1998
- Awards presentation, March 26, 1997
- Washington, D.C., undated
- Race relations panel, August 1997
- Consensus panel, April 1997
- Sessions and committees, 1993-1998
- James Banks publications committee conference call, June 26, 1997